Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Okay,
so today's דף daf is what we, it's כד kaf daled again,
we're a little bit ahead, and we pick up on כד עמוד
א kaf daled amud aleph about eight lines, ten lines from the
bottom, the two dots, ובתרומה אם נטמאת וכו. u-vi-trumah im nitmeis etcetera.
So here's another difference that on תרומה trumah if one hand becomes
טמא tamei the other does not, whereby קודש kodesh if one hand
becomes טמא tamei the other does. Now there's an adjustment right at
the outset that there's an interesting debate between רש"י Rashi and תוספות.
Tosfos. רש"י Rashi assumes what it means is, remember if your hand
is טמא tamei it's only your hand, that means you touched something
that's a rabbinic טומאה tumah that makes your hand a שני. sheni.
Now
presumably you washed both hands because your hands in general are considered
שני, sheni, but you went ahead and you washed both hands and
you were watching them and making sure that they didn't touch anything,
so they were טהור, tahor, and then one hand lo and behold
touches something that's a rabbinic problem so that becomes a שני. sheni.
So how does the other hand become a שני sheni by קודש?
kodesh? So רש"י Rashi says it means if hand one touches hand
two. Normally they can't do anything because hand one is a שני
sheni and a שני sheni can't make you know your other hand
into a שני, sheni, and the חידוש chiddush is that by קודש
kodesh it can but only if it touches it. תוספות Tosfos goes
so far to say that no by קודש kodesh it's automatic. As
soon as one hand becomes טמא tamei we consider both hands טמא.
tamei. Okay so that's just a basic debate in terms of what
the משנה mishna means that it says by קודש kodesh one hand
טמא tamei makes the other hand טמא. tamei. But that's by קודש
kodesh and not by תרומה. trumah. So let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. אמר רב שיזבי בחיבורין שנו. Amar Rav Shizbi be-chiburin shanu.
We're only talking about when it is in connection. אבל שלא בחיבורין
לא, Aval she-lo be-chiburin lo, but not in connection no. Now what
does this idea mean in connection? Again there are two versions of
it. תוספות Tosfos has, and I don't know where my markers are,
תוספות Tosfos has that the two versions of it, I'll get my
markers, excuse me.
Okay
so
according to תוספות Tosfos here's the thing that is going to make
you טמא. tamei. Okay here's you, okay, whatever here's you. Okay so
what's חיבורין? chiburin? So according to תוספות Tosfos what חיבורין chiburin means
is this hand is touching it okay and then at the same
time that hand is touching it here the you know a classic
example of something that'll make you טמא tamei ironically is ספרי קודש.
sifrei kodesh. So here's your ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, very ironic but
that's the example תוספות Tosfos uses. Okay here's your ספר תורה, Sefer
Torah, this hand is touching it so that hand becomes a שני,
sheni, that's a 2 a שני, sheni, and then this hand is
touching that hand or touching and therefore that hand also because it's
like in connection right it's sort of electricity so although it's not
directly touching the thing so that's חיבורין chiburin so that hand also
becomes a שני. sheni. That's תוספות's Tosfos version of חיבורין. chiburin. All
right so they're in connection. As opposed to saying that even just
because one hand touches and then the other and then it'll you
know and then that makes it no only when they're in connection.
רש"י Rashi has it the opposite. רש"י Rashi has it that here
okay your hand is a... hold on let me just get רש"י.
Rashi.
Right רש"י Rashi has it like this it's going the opposite direction.
Here is your קודש kodesh okay whatever it'll be I don't know
here is your oil that you're going to bring to the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay here's your טהור tahor hand touching it the
קודש kodesh and here is your... whatever...
and here is your טמא tamei hand touching your טהור tahor hand.
So this is what is טמא tamei and it is indirectly transferring
it to your טהור tahor hand טמא tamei to your טהור tahor
hand to the קודש. kodesh. Okay? So for תוספות Tosfos the issue
is the, it
is
the, how it's becoming טמא. tamei. Your hand becomes, one hand touches
the thing that causes טומאה tumah that transfers it to the other
hand if they're touching. For רש"י Rashi it's how it's transferring the
טומאה. tumah. Your טהור tahor hand is touching the קודש kodesh the
טהור tahor thing but the טמא tamei hand transfers it to the
קודש. kodesh. Okay? But either way that's pretty clear what's going on
there. But anyway it only works through some type of electricity. Either
the way it receives the טומאה tumah is one is touching the
other or the way it transfers the טומאה tumah is one is
touching the other. Okay so that's the issue of חיבורין. chiburin. אבל
שלא בחיבורין לא. Aval she-lo be-chiburin lo. If it is not through
that if they're separate then the טומאה's tumah not going to transfer
from one hand to the other either be received by it or
transfer through it to the other thing. So the גמרא Gemara says
איתיביה אביי Eisivei Abaye or Abaye asked on this יד נגובה. מטמא
חברתה yad neguva metamei chaverta, לטמא letamei, לקודש אבל לא לתרומה. aval
lo latrumah,
If you have a hand that is dry, then it makes it
even if it's dry is the point, because if it's wet, when
something is wet and something a שני sheini touches it, then the
wet thing becomes a ראשון, rishon, and that's just makes it much
easier to transfer טומאה tumah if something is wet. So here the
point is it's not wet. If it's wet, it could work even
maybe for תרומה trumah and for חולין. chullin. It's dry. Okay. So
even if it's dry, מטמא חברתה לטמא לקודש, mitamei chavertah letamei lakodesh,
it makes the other hand טמא tamei to make קודש טמא, kodesh
tamei, אבל לא לתרומה, aval lo l'trumah, not for תרומה. trumah. דברי
רבי. divrei Rabbi. Fine, that's more or less what we said. רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yose bei Rabbi Yehuda omer, רבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose bei Rabbi Yehuda says, לפסול אבל לא לטמא.
lifsol aval lo letamei. It only makes it פסול, pasul, it doesn't
make it טמא. tamei, So when it makes the קודש kodesh invalid,
right, here's the point. The קודש kodesh is a, your hand is
a שני, sheini, okay? That's the idea. So if your שני sheini
was going to come into contact with קודש, kodesh right, it would
make קודש kodesh, into a שלישי. shlishi. Now that's considered לטמא, letamei.
because as we know קודש kodesh can pass that on one degree
further to a רביעי, revii, that's called לטמא. To call it פסול
pasul means it ends, would only make it into a רביעי. revii.
So his point is that he actually is saying that he says
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר לפסול Rabbi Yose bei Rabbi Yehuda omer
lifsol when it makes the קודש טמא, kodesh tamei, it doesn't make
it a שלישי, shlishi, it essentially makes it only a רביעי revii
even with this idea that, you know, one hand is מטמא mitamei
the other. אבל לא לטמא. aval lo letamei. Okay, so we'll get
back to that in a minute. Now, אי אמרת בשלמא שלא בחיבורין,
i marta bishlama shelo bechiburin, היינו רבותא דנגובה. hainu revuta deniguva.
If you're telling me that the hands are not like in, you
know, directly in contact, touching one, touching the other, touching the other
thing, so it's all this like, you know, everything, you know, all
direct, I understand the חידוש chidush that it's
dry. Because if it's not, if it's not,
if it's not like here, you know,
let's
take, you know, let's take רש"י Rashi תוספות Tosafos' example, maybe it's
easier. Here's my ספר sefer which causes טומאה, tumah, believe it or
not. Okay, so here one hand touches it, okay, and here the
other touches that. Okay, so if the idea is בחיבורין, bechiburin, then
presumably the logic is not that I say this, here's the different
conceptual logic. First I touch this and my hand becomes a שני,
sheini, and then I say that by just touching my other hand,
even when they're not sort of direct and in, you know, all
in contact at the same time, this becomes a שני, sheini, then
the conceptual logic you're using is that it transfers, right? This is
טמא tamei. and it transfers like טומאה tumah normally transfers. Well, normally
we wouldn't have a שני sheini making something else into a שני.
sheini. You would need liquid or whatever in order to make one
hand make the other טמא. tamei, That's a big חידוש chidush that
even if this is dry, this hand as a שני sheini can
make this other hand into a שני. sheini. That's a big חידוש
chidush and therefore you have to say even if it's dry it
can do that. Okay, but what's the logic if I say, you
know what, this'll never do anything, this doesn't do anything? Okay, but
if you've got it going like this, then this hand becomes טמא.
tamei So then the logic is not that this is טמא tamei.
and it makes this טמא. tamei. The logic is that it's being
like I am touching this, right, in extension, correct? You see that?
If I demand that it only works in this context, then it's
not really this is making this טמא, tamei it's like this is
indirectly touching it. Whether it's receiving the טומאה tumah like תוספות Tosafos
says, or transferring the טומאה tumah onto the other thing, it's working
as one big extended thing. So the גמרא Gemara says if that's
what you limit your case to, when they're in contact, touching one,
touching the other, then there's no חידוש chidush that's saying that this
is dry, because the logic is not that this made this טמא,
tamei. the logic is that this is indirectly touching the other thing.
So why do you have to say dry if we're limiting ourselves
to a case of בחיבורין? bechiburin? So let's read that. אי אמרת
בשלמא שלא בחיבורין, i marta bishlama shelo bechiburin, היינו רבותא דנגובה, hainu
revuta deniguva, if one makes the other טמא, tamei, you know, independently
when they're not all directly in sort of like, you know, all
touching the thing, היינו רבותא דנגובה, hainu revuta deniguva, then you have
to say even if it's dry, because normally that wouldn't be able
to happen. אבל אי אמרת בחיבורין אין שלא בחיבורין לא, aval i
marta bechiburin in shelo bechiburin lo,
but if you just tell me that it's only if it's while
it's sort of in direct, you know, sort of A touching B
touching C, so מאי רבותא דנגובה, mai revuta deniguva, then it's not
based about the normal idea of the hand transferring to the other
hand. It's all like an extended way of touching. So then why
do you have to tell me even if it's dry? That there's
no חידוש chidush in that, conceptually it's a completely different point. Okay,
so that's the גמרא's Gemara challenge to that idea that limits it
to this case of indirect touching. איתמר נמי, itmar nami, it was
also taught. Now there's a whole question what the נמי nami means
because this next thing we're going to teach does not seem to
be directly supporting what we just said, but anyway, it's certainly relevant,
a relevant ברייתא. brayta. Let's take a look. אמר ריש לקיש, amar
Reish Lakish, said ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, לא שנו אלא ידו וידו,
lo shanu ela yado veyado, אבל יד חברו לא. aval yad chavero
lo.
It's only when it is, here's another interesting thing. I'm touching, my
one hand is טמא, tamei, is touching David's hand there that's טהור.
tahor. Does that also... or does it only by קודש kodesh or
is it only when my left hand touches my right hand? Let's
say I touch somebody else's hand. So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says,
only when you touch your own hand. רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan
amar, אחד ידו ואחד יד חבירו. echad yado ve-echad yad chaveiro. Even
if you touch somebody else's hand, by קודש kodesh one hand can
make another hand טמא. tamei, ובאותו היד לפסול אבל לא לטמא. U-be-oto
ha-yad lifsol aval lo le-tamei.
Now, and that is ובאותו היד, u-be-oto ha-yad,
okay, meaning now what ובאותו היד u-be-oto ha-yad means is, here my
left hand became טמא. tamei, That made, boom, my right hand טמא,
tamei. right, because it's קודש. kodesh So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says,
you know, this hand, this left hand, can go make David's hand
טמא tamei. because this is the real or original thing that's טמא.
tamei, But this right hand that became טמא tamei because of the
left, that's already just an, you know,
like an extended, it's one degree removed. So even though this is
a שני sheni and it made this into a שני, sheni, this
cannot make somebody else's hand טמא. tamei. Okay, you got it? This
is the real thing that's טמא. tamei Right, this is the real
thing that's טמא tamei. because of the מעלה בקודש ma'alah be-kodesh we
allow it to make the other hand טמא, tamei. but this other
hand now can't continue that on. Okay, but this, the original one,
says רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, not only can make your own hand
טמא, tamei it can make somebody else's hand טמא tamei, as well.
Okay, so there's two points. One is the power is only invested
in the original hand. But the second point, which makes a lot
of sense, we won't belabor that, but the second point, the real
debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is
that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says this hand can even make somebody
else's hand טמא. tamei, Okay, so we're going to get look at
that in a minute, but that's just right now the immediate debate.
ובאותו היד לפסול אבל לא לטמא. U-be-oto ha-yad lifsol aval lo le-tamei.
And now the other point that we said earlier, you know, we
quoted that says that even when this can make
קודש kodesh מלהטמא קודש, mi-le-tamei kodesh, and it's a שני, sheni, it
doesn't make קודש kodesh. into a שלישי. shlishi. You know, the fact,
it really, this idea that now this other hand has become טמא,
tamei that only makes קודש kodesh into a רביעי. revii. It's פוסל
קודש, posel kodesh, it's not מטמא קודש. metamei kodesh. Okay. Now מאי?
mai? ממי? mi-mai? מדקתני סיפא, Mi-de-katani seifa, so where
do you get this? Because it says at the end, שהיד מטמא
חברתה לקודש אבל לא לתרומה. she-ha-yad metamei chavertah le-kodesh aval lo li-terumah.
Where do you get the idea that it only is פוסל, posel,
it's not מטמא? metamei? Maybe if the other hand becomes a שני
sheni as well, it can make קודש kodesh into a שלישי. shlishi.
No, because the end of the משנה mishnah said, it repeated the
idea. The משנה mishnah said, because one hand is מטמא metamei its
friend, its other hand for קודש, kodesh but not for תרומה. terumah.
הא תו למה לי הא תנא ליה רישא? Ha tu lamah li
ha-tana leh reisha? So that's repeating what it initially said. It said,
the difference is that one hand is מטמא metamei another, you know,
for קודש kodesh and not for תרומה, terumah, and then it repeated
it. Why did it repeat it in
the
משנה? mishnah? אלא לאו שמע מינה לאתויי יד חבירו, Ela lav shema
minah le-atuyei yad chaveiro, to tell you that not only, the reason
it repeated that one hand can make another hand טמא tamei. is
to tell you not only can it make your other hand טמא,
tamei, it can make somebody else's other hand טמא. tamei ואף ריש
לקיש הדר ביה, Ve-af Reish Lakish hadar beh, and even ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish retracted and wound up agreeing to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
that one hand can make another hand טמא. tamei, How do you
know it? ואף ריש לקיש הדר ביה, Ve-af Reish Lakish hadar beh,
דאמר רבי יונה אמר רבי אמי אמר ריש לקיש, de-amar Rabbi Yonah
amar Rabbi Ami amar Reish Lakish, אחד ידו ואחד יד חבירו, echad
yado ve-echad yad chaveiro,
whether your hand or even somebody else's hand, it can make somebody
else's hand טמא. tamei. ובאותו היד, U-be-oto ha-yad, only the original hand
can make yours or somebody else's טמא. tamei. It can't, a derivative
hand can't do it. ולפסול אבל לא לטמא, U-le-fisol aval lo le-tamei,
and again, only to make קודש kodesh, into
a רביעי, revii, לפסול אבל לא לטמא. lifsol aval lo le-tamei. So
what we have here is introduced, number one, the idea that this
power to make another hand טמא tamei. is limited to the original
hand, which makes sense, but also this interesting debate of what can
it do, can it do this to your friend's hand? Now what
does this have to do with the previous issue? So תוספות Tosafot
says,
let me just check תוספות. Tosafot.
I know that's actually not exactly what I wanted to say. So
the interesting question to ask is, is the debate of רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish about somebody else's hand tied
into this issue of the, of the idea of, what do you
call it? Of the idea of this extended touch, because there was
an approach that wanted to limit the idea of one hand being
מטמא metamei the other, not when it just exists independently, this, this
became טמא tamei. and now this touches this, but only when they're
sort of, you know, in, like, you know, conducting electricity, one touching
the other touching the other thing. So the גמרא Gemara doesn't directly
connect it, but it's certainly suggestive to think that it's a related
debate. If this hand can go ahead and be מטמא metamei somebody
else's, right? If they're both my hands, right, if I'm
going
ahead... It makes a lot more sense just speak about a type
of an extended touch when it's both they're both my hands, right?
If it's one is yours and one is mine, I mean you
could talk about it, but they're two different agents involved, it's harder
to think about it as an extended touch. So this type if
you limit it to this case when it's all in the same
act, you know, then it makes more sense that they're both my
hands. But if you say that even when they're not in the
same act, this became טמא tamei and now this can touch this
and make this טמא, tamei then it's pretty much just as logical
the same way it can make this טמא tamei that it can
make your hand טמא tamei, as well. Right? So this debate of
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish and רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, the גמרא Gemara
doesn't exactly connect the dots, but whether it can make somebody else's
hand or only your own could somewhat be made similar to this
question of, you know, of what do you call it, about whether
you're limiting it to a case of an of like only when
it's A is touching B touching C, only an extension or even
when they're separate moments. Okay, that's one way you can see some
correlation. Another way, and this is what תוספות Tosafot points out about
a possible correlation is: does the second hand that become טמא, tamei
does that make קודש kodesh into a שלישי Shlishi or into a
רביעי? Revi'i? Okay, and תוספות Tosafot says the same point: if I
am saying that the way it happens is if it's going like
this, then it's sort of like if I if this is the
only case that it works, then it's sort of like this directly
touched the קודש. kodesh This directly touched either the קודש Kodesh or
the טומאה, Tumah, because the whole idea is we see it as
a form of extended touch.
I thought this was it?
No, so that's the question: is that only might be according to
רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, so if you say
that you see that you limit it like that this is the
only case that it works, then conceptually that's because it's like this
directly touched. So if this directly touched, maybe it works just as
powerfully as the original hand. Whereas if you say that it goes
like that, it goes in separate steps, this becomes טמא tamei and
then it touches this and this becomes טמא, tamei, then conceptually this
is a derivative. And therefore it doesn't have the same power, the
same strength as the original hand. Okay, so there are these three
different issues. Number one: is it only the basic issue is: what's
the fundamental case? Separate moments touching this and transferring it, or one
extended process? And that debate could it could impact two other debates.
Number one is: what's the story about a friend's hand? Friend's hand
makes sense if it's separate moments, doesn't make sense if you're seeing
it as an extended act not as much. And: what's the power
of the second hand? Is it equal to the first or is
it derivative? And that could also be: if it's like this, it's
probably equal to the first. If it's like this, separate moments, then
it's probably weaker than the first hand. Yes, Michael?
I was going to say
is
that to say that conceptually they're separate hands it doesn't really make
so much sense, because if I touch a שרץ, sheretz, it's not
like I say that finger is טמא tamei and not the rest
of me, right?
Yeah, well the whole point is that rabbinically you have to accept
the idea that just the hand can become טמא, tamei, but once
you do, then you work within that system. Okay, so now let's
take a look. The גמרא Gemara says like this,
right, so in the end, right, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who says,
who says, right, when and then notice that when ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish comes around to רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan idea, he says two
things. First he says when it says אף ריש לקיש הדר ביה
דאמר רבי יוחנן אמר רב אמר ריש לקיש אחד ידו ואחד יד
חבירו, af Resh Lakish hadar beih d'amar Rabbi Yochanan amar Rav amar
Resh Lakish echad yado v'echad yad chaveiro, so he comes around to
רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan idea that it could be מטמא metamei somebody
else's hand, but באותו היד b'oto hayad and it's only the original
has that power, לפסול אבל לא לטמא, lifsol aval lo l'tamei, that
when he says it could do somebody else's hand, that he also
says that the second hand is one is derivative and weaker, right?
So those are linked ideas. If it can do somebody else's hand,
then it means it's not looking at it as an extended act.
Okay, and once that's true, then it means that the second hand
is going to be weaker than the first and only לפסול אבל
לא לטמא. lifsol aval lo l'tamei. And now the גמרא Gemara questions
this.
Yeah.
I guess it's implicit in the way you're describing it, maybe you
even said it, it's really like electricity.
Yeah, exactly.
It's really like amazing, right. Okay.
זה לפסול אבל לא לטמא תנאי היא.
zeh lifsol
aval lo l'tamei Tannai hi. Now this issue about the power of
the second hand, is it like the first and can be מטמא
metamei קודש Kodesh. or only derivative and make קודש Kodesh פסול? pasul?
That's a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. דתנן d'tnan in the משנה, Mishnah,
כל הפוסל בתרומה מטמא ידים להיות שניות. kol haposel b'Terumah metamei yadayim
lihyot shniyot. Anything that invalidates תרומה, Terumah, okay, that may meaning that's
a שני, shani, so it can also make the hands into a
שני. shani. That's the idea of let's say we gave an example
of like ספרי קודש. Sifrei Kodesh. ויד מטמא חבירתה, v'yad metamei chaveiratah,
and one hand makes another hand טמא, tamei דברי רבי יהושע. divrei
Rabbi Yehoshua. וחכמים אומרים ידים שניות הן, vachachamim omrim yadayim shniyot hen,
and the חכמים Chachamim say no no your hands are a שני
shani if either you're not paying attention to them or they touch
something that's טמא tamei, that's a שני, shani, ואין שני עושה שני,
v'ein shani oseh shani, and one hand which is a שני shani
can't make the other hand into a שני. shani. So it sounds
like the חכמים Chachamim here disagree with this idea that by קודש
Kodesh one hand is
מטמא metamei the other.
You said by קודש Kodesh ואין שני עושה שני. v'ein shani oseh
shani. So the גמרא Gemara doesn't want to think that the חכמים
chachamim disagree with the basic rule of our משנה mishna that one
hand is מטמא metamei the other. So it says, okay, here's what
they're saying: one hand doesn't make the other into a שני, sheini,
but it would make the other into a שלישי, shlishi, which means
that the second hand can be פוסל קודש posel kodesh but not
מטמא metamei it, which is that idea of derivative, okay? So isn't
that exactly the debate, that according to רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua the
second hand has the same power, it's a שני, sheini, and according
to the חכמים chachamim the second hand is a שלישי? shlishi? So
the גמרא Gemara says, no, דילמא לא שני עביד ולא שלישי. dilma
lo sheini avid v'lo shlishi. Maybe the חכמים chachamim completely reject the
idea that one hand is מטמא metamei the other. They're not just
saying it's weaker, they're saying it doesn't work. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אלא ela fine, that maybe that's not the debate of whether
the second hand is a שני sheini or שלישי, shlishi, but let's
try this. כהני תנאי, ke'hani tana'ei, the following תנאי. tana'ei. דתניא, detanya,
we taught in a ברייתא, braisa, יד נגובה yad niguvah. מטמא metamei
חברתה, this is what we started quoting on עמוד א'. amud aleph.
Even if the hand is dry, it's מטמא metamei the other one
לטמא בקודש letamei bakodesh אבל לא lo, לתרומה, דברי רבי יוסי. divrei
Rebbi Yosi. And it makes the second hand טמא tamei, that it
can make קודש Kodesh טמא, tamei but it won't affect תרומה. trumah.
This is all a דין din by קודש. Kodesh But the phrase
it uses is לטמא בקודש, letamei bakodesh, to make קודש kodesh. טמא,
tamei which means the second hand is considered a שני sheini and
makes קודש kodesh a שלישי. shlishi. And then the גמרא Gemara says,
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר אותה יד לפסול אבל לא לטמא. Rebbi
Yosi b'Rebbi Yehuda omer otah yad livsol aval lo letamei. No, it
can only make קודש kodesh into a רביעי, revii, it cannot make
it into a שלישי, shlishi, the second hand is only a, goes
down a level, is a שלישי. shlishi. Okay. It doesn't have enough
power. So we have these again three debates. Number one is what's
the story about somebody else's hand? Number two is what's the, is
the second hand have the same level, is it a שני sheini
or does it go down, is it a שלישי? shlishi? And then
we have the debate of is it only when it's in connecting
and sort of like electricity or only separate acts? And the first
two debates seem dependent on the second. If it's only in electricity,
it makes sense that it's all both your hands and that then
the hands have the same level because it's all an extended act.
If it's not in electricity, separate acts, then it's really transferring it
and then it makes sense it could transfer to a friend's hand
and it makes sense that the second hand would be a derivative,
would be a שלישי, shlishi, not a שני. sheini. Okay.
Yeah. Is this the first possibility in this last point where it's
only when they're touching? Yeah. When they stop touching, it goes back
to the former state or the טומאה tumah state remains?
No, then the טומאה tumah state remains, but the way it received
the טומאה tumah was in that moment of touching.
Yeah, didn't go back, correct, correct.
Okay. אוכלין אוכלין נגובים בידיים מסואבות. ochlin ochlin neguvim b'yadayim mesuavos. So
getting down to some of the last ones, if you have food
that has never come in contact with liquid, so it's not only
that it's not טמא, tamei, it's not susceptible to becoming טמא. tamei.
It's never been in contact with liquid since it's been let's say
cut off the tree or the animal שחט shechted it and whatever
and made into food. And therefore it's even if something טמא tamei
touches it, it's not טמא. tamei. It needs to first come in
contact with liquid. Nevertheless, so if it's תרומה, trumah, your hands could
be טמא, tamei, no problem, you know the food is Teflon right
now. But for קודש, kodesh, you still have to wash your hands.
So let's see why. דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braisa,
אמר רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס, amar Rebbi Chanina ben Antignos, וכי יש
נגיבה לקודש? v'chi yeish negiva l'kodesh? Now he says, I don't understand
why this is even a חידוש chiddush that you have to wash
your hands for קודש kodesh in this case. By קודש, kodesh, there's
no need for it to be wet in order to be susceptible.
Being dry is a meaningless idea by קודש. kodesh. Why? והלא חיבת
הקודש מכשרתן. vehalo chibas hakodesh machshartan. We have a general principle that
by קודש, kodesh, like if you've got your wine or oil that
you're going to put in a כלי שרת kli shares and bring
to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash etc., that the very fact that
they have this holiness, that makes them more susceptible. You know, that's
like an idea that the holier something is, the more vulnerable and
sensitive. So there's a general idea that קודש kodesh can become טמא
tamei without being wet. So this wasn't some new מעלה ma'alah that's
about washing your hands. The whole concept is, of course, it doesn't
matter by קודש kodesh if it's wet or dry. It's just as
bad wet and dry. So there's not a חידוש chiddush here to
even begin with. Okay, so what's this whole idea, oh, even if
it's dry you have to wash your hands? It doesn't even, of
course, that's irrelevant by קודש. kodesh. So let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. צריכא, tzericha, here's the case. כגון דחב ליה חבירו לתוך
פיו, k'gon dechav leih chaveiro l'soch piv, or דחב ליה לעצמו בקושי
בקרקע. dechav leih l'atzmo bekushi bekarka. Okay, so you basically are going
ahead and you have your hands aren't washed, fine, but somebody
puts food... You
had some little cubes of meat from your שלמים *shelomim*, a toothpick
is a כלי keli. עץ *kli etz* that doesn't have a בית
קיבול *beit kibul*, so it's totally טהור tahor, *tahor*, it doesn't transfer
טומאה tumah *tumah*. So you put your toothpick in and you're chewing
your שלמים *shelomim* meat. Okay, so even though your hands are a
שני *sheni*, no touching, or somebody else puts the meat in your
mouth, no touching, look Ma, no hands, right? And then there you
are chewing and then you want to go ahead and, oh you
know what? You know what goes good with this meat? A little
onion would go good with it. ובקש לאכול צנון ובצל של חולין
chulin עמהם *U-bikesh le-echol tzon u-vatzal she-chullin ima-hem*. And you go ahead
and you want to go ahead and eat some onion and or
some radish together with your meat. So you say look, my hands
are a שני *sheni*, that's true, but I would never touch קודש
kodesh, *kodesh* with this hand, even dry קודש kodesh. *kodesh* of course
not, you know that the whatever, קודש kodesh, *kodesh* is always susceptible.
But somebody else put some nice שלמים *shelomim* meat in my mouth
and I have some chopped up onions, let me take some chopped
up onions of חולין chulin. *chullin* and throw that in my mouth.
So who cares that my hand is a שני *sheni*? These chopped
up onions were never got wet, are never susceptible to טומאה tumah
*tumah*, right? And let me therefore take these chopped up onions and
they remain טהור tahor. *tahor* and throw it in my mouth.
Onions are always, things always have, that doesn't,
yeah, they always have sort of juices, it doesn't really count. Okay
fine. So can I do that? Okay, עמהם *ima-hem*, לקודש גזרו בהן
רבנן ולתרומה לא גזרו בהן רבנן *le-kodesh gazaru ba-hen rabanan u-le-trumah lo
gazaru ba-hen rabanan*. So what would you think? If I were to
say to you: Michael, can I do that? I'm chewing קודש kodesh.
*kodesh*, God forbid my hands should ever touch the meat in my
mouth, but can I take a whole pile of, you know, of
onions, of chopped up onions and throw it in my mouth? What
would you tell me?
We're all getting so crazy over קודש kodesh, *kodesh*, I say no.
Why not? What might happen? From throwing it in my mouth? Maybe
I'll touch the meat in my mouth with my hands. Don't get
your hands close to your mouth and feed yourself with your hands,
right, if you've got that קודש kodesh *kodesh* meat in your mouth.
Okay, so do we have to be concerned about that? So by
קודש kodesh *kodesh* we are concerned, don't do that, but by תרומה
terumah, *trumah*, if you're chewing תרומה terumah *trumah*, then we would allow
you to actually put the חולין *chullin* in your mouth and we
wouldn't be afraid you would touch the תרומה terumah *trumah*. So that's
how we're framing the case, not whether you have to wash your
hands before handling קודש kodesh. *kodesh*, that would be obvious, but that
you're eating קודש kodesh *kodesh* and you have to wash your hands
before feeding yourself חולין *chullin* if you've got קודש Kodesh, *kodesh* in
your mouth. So for קודש Kodesh *kodesh* you do and for תרומה
terumah. *trumah* you do not.
I just don't understand how anybody ate anything.
All right. האונן ומחוסר כיפורים *Ha-onen ve-mchusar kipurim*,
last one, if somebody who stopped to be, you know, was an
אונן *onen*, had lost a relative, and now the relative is buried,
and somebody who was a מחוסר כיפורים *mchusar kipurim* was not able
to eat קרבנות *korbanot* because he had to bring a final sacrifice
to make him טהור tahor *tahor*, and now he's able to eat
קרבנות *korbanot*. So for קודש Kodesh, *kodesh* he has to dunk in
a מקוה mikveh, *mikvah* before he can now go ahead and eat
קרבנות *korbanot*, but not for תרומה terumah *trumah*. מאי טעמא mai ta'ama,
*Mai ta'ama*? Why is that? כיוון דהאידנא הוה אסירי *Keivan de-ha-idna hava
asiri*, so until now, somebody who was an אונן *onen* and somebody
who was מחוסר כיפורים *mchusar kipurim* could eat תרומה terumah, *trumah*, the
only thing is that an אונן *onen* and מחוסר כיפורים *mchusar kipurim*
cannot eat קודש Kodesh *kodesh*. So since until this moment they were
in a state of forbidden to קודש Kodesh, *kodesh*, הטריכו רבנן טבילה
*hatrichu rabanan tvilah*, and now they're changing their status, so to formally
mark the new status, go into the מקוה *mikvah*. Now that by
the way makes sense because the status changes here outside of the
person. The person stops being an אונן *onen* because something outside of
him changed, the dead person was buried. Somebody stops being a מחוסר
כיפורים *mchusar kipurim* because something outside of him changed, a קרבן *korban*
was brought in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*. But what
happens as a result is his own personal status is now different.
So to mark the change of your own personal status, we need
something actually to do to your body, go to the מקוה *mikvah*
and that'll formally mark the change of your status and then you'll
be able to eat קודש Kodesh, *kodesh*, and that makes a lot
of sense. So with that we finished the ten מעלות *ma'alot* and
we get to the next משנה Mishnah *mishnah*. Yeah.
So this thought is completely obvious and never dawned upon me, there's
something about the system, like I could never eat תרומה terumah *trumah*.
Right. But I can eat something which is even higher.
It's a good point. Right. It's an interesting phenomenon that's built into
the system. I can eat קודש kodesh *kodesh*, but
I can never eat תרומה terumah *trumah*.
Right. At a higher level. Right. That's a very good point.
I don't know what that means, but it's like really intriguing.
You're right. I hadn't sort of exactly faced it, framed it like
that. It's an excellent point. Right.
Like as he brings a שלמים *shelomim*, he can't eat a חטאת
hattas, *chatas* or an אשם *asham*, but if you bring your קרבן
*korban*, you can eat the meat of your שלמים *shelomim* in ירושלים
*Yerushalayim*.
And that's קודש kodesh, *kodesh*. Right. But I can never eat תרומה
terumah *trumah*. Right.
Ever. Right. Okay, now we are, now we're done with all of
these stratifications of different levels. A lot of this has been different
levels of treating קודש kodesh *kodesh* and תרומה terumah. *trumah*, but there's
also been implicit and explicit different levels of people based on which
sort of class they're part of and which degrees they observe. And
now we start getting to the next משנה *mishnah*. Right. Right. Right.
Okay, now we are, now we're done with all of this stratifications
of different levels. A lot of this has been different levels of
treating קודש kodesh and תרומה, terumah. but there's also been implicit and
explicit different levels of people based on which sort of class they're
part of and which degrees they observe. And now we start getting
to the transition of how actually we believe people that we normally
wouldn't believe in under circumstances, particularly as it gets to the רגל,
regel, but we're going to see even areas even before the רגל
regel where we're prepared to sort of do away with some of
those distinctions. Yes.
I was just trying to get my mind around is one thing.
With the תרומה terumah case, you weren't concerned if you're eating the
dry whatever it is, right? Yeah. But don't you have saliva in
your mouth?
Yeah, but we're not afraid that you'll touch with your hands, that
your hands won't get into your mouth and touch the stuff that's
in your mouth.
No, but your hands will touch the saliva, and the saliva then
מטמא metamei the תרומה terumah that's in your...
I guess I think we're not concerned about. You mean like even
if it... yeah.
When you put your fingers on your lips to put it in,
the moment they touch your lips it's all moist.
I'm not sure if saliva that has not been separated out of
your mouth has a status of משקה. mashkeh. Have to double check
that. Okay. All right. חומר בתרומה. Chomer b'terumah. Now, there's a stringency
in תרומה. terumah, רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, it's actually funny that it
introduces it by חומר בתרומה, chomer b'terumah, because really what it's going
to introduce is a leniency, okay? So let's take a look. רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in Judea, which is where Jerusalem is, which is
going to be relevant, נאמנים על טהרת יין ושמן כל ימות השנה.
ne'emanim al taharat yayin v'shemen kol yemot hashanah. That in general, and
we've already seen this, that you'll trust people, even the עמי הארץ,
am'ei ha'aretz, you trust them when it goes gets to issues about
קודש, kodesh, right? Here's that irony again: the holier it is, but
because you don't want to exclude them from the בית המקדש, Beit
HaMikdash. you trust them when it comes to the טהרה tahara of
קודש. kodesh So the purity of
יין ושמן, yayin v'shemen, of wine and oil, those are the types
of things that they would bring in vessels and that they could
sanctify for to bring for the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So if
they're bringing wine and oil which is קודש, kodesh not said explicitly
here but assumed, then they're believed כל ימות השנה, kol yemot hashanah,
the entire year to say that they kept their קודש טהור. kodesh
tahor. For reasons that we've seen, maybe they're more scrupulous, but more
significantly you don't want to cause them to be completely you know
marginalized, completely disenfranchised. So there you believe them כל ימות השנה, kol
yemot hashanah, the entire year. ובשעת הגתות והבדים אף על התרומה. Uv'sha'at
hagattot v'habaddim af al haterumah.
Now, in a way this is חומר בתרומה chomer b'terumah meaning, yes,
I misstated. חומר בתרומה Chomer b'terumah means a greater stringency of תרומה
Terumah. than קודש. kodesh That's what it means, I'm sorry. So קודש,
Kodesh here's the irony, קודש kodesh you believe them the whole year,
that's what we've said, right? Because otherwise they'll go and build their
own בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash, They'll be completely you know excluded. So
קודש kodesh you believe them to be careful the whole year if
they bring stuff that they say is קודש. kodesh But תרומה, Terumah
you don't believe them the whole year, okay? Let them give their
תרומה Terumah to a כהן עם הארץ. Kohen am ha'aretz. That we've
said before. So that's ironic, but תרומה Terumah. is more חמור chamur
than קודש in terms of believing the עם הארץ. am ha'aretz. However,
even acknowledging that for תרומה Terumah, we generally don't believe them to
keep it טהור, tahor. we do believe them a certain time of
the year. What time of the year do we believe them? ובשעת
הגתות והבדים, Uv'sha'at hagattot v'habaddim, the time of pressing of the olives
and of pressing of the grapes, that's the גת gat and pressing
of the olives is the בד. bad. Then, when they're pressing it,
אף על התרומה, af al haterumah, they're producing their wine and oil,
right? It's the time when they're harvesting and all the grapes and
they're pressing it and producing their wine and oil, then and the
עם הארץ am ha'aretz comes to a כהן Kohen and says, I
just harvested all my grapes, we made all this wine, here's your
תרומה. Terumah. And it's the time of when this activity is going
on, then we believe them even for תרומה. Terumah Now, during that
season, now why do we believe them even for תרומה Terumah in
that time? If in general why not just give it to your
friend the כהן עם הארץ? Kohen am ha'aretz? Don't give it to
me, I don't trust you. So if you look at רש"י, Rashi,
רש"י Rashi says, four lines from the bottom, ובשעת הגתות והבדים הכל
מטהרין את כליהם. Uv'sha'at hagattot v'habaddim hakol metaharin et keleihem. There, since
you know everybody got into the process, like everybody goes out and
bakes their מצה, matzah, everybody the whole community knows it's time for
the oil press, the first thing you do is you כשר kasher
all your כלי. Like before פסח, Pesach, right? And we're going to
have in the שול shul a big boiling vat thing of water,
everybody bring their כליהם. keleihem. I'm being a little funny because that's
what you do at פסח. Pesach. But here when you need boiling
water, but basically this would be part of the communal experience when
it comes time to do this once a year when we begin
the process. We all take all our stuff to the מקוה, טובל
tovel everything, everything is טהור. tahor. We're going to process it and
at that time you can assume that when the תרומה Terumah, is
produced at that time, right after they were מטהר metaher it, that
it's going to be טהור tahor? and you can accept it. Now
that is a practical reason why we could assume it's better. However,
later רש"י Rashi says that there's also a little bit of a
self-interest reason why we believe people at this time. So you tell
me what's the self-interest reason?
It's the main time of production.
Because you'd have to tell the כהנים Kohanim that they can't get
ninety percent of the תרומה, Terumah right? The עמי הארץ am'ei ha'aretz
were a lot more numerous than the חברים. chaverim. They probably also
were the people that were much more involved in agriculture and... business
and so on than the חברים. Chaveirim. So they're producing, let's say,
90% of the תרומה. Terumah So you're going to tell me that
the כהנים חברים Kohanim Chaveirim have to be excluded from all of
that? Oh, you know what? At the time when they're pressing the
oil, then you can believe everybody. And that's when most of the
תרומה Terumah, is going to get produced and distributed. So a רש"י,
Rashi, I'm not saying this, a later רש"י Rashi says this, so
A, there's some facts on the ground that allow us to say
this because everybody is טובל tovel their כלים, keilim, but there are
also certain policy issues. The same way there were policy issues by
believing them when it comes to קודש, right? So there might be
some facts on the ground that help us say it, but there's
also like overriding policy considerations that create that tell us to believe
them by קודש and to believe them by תרומה Terumah at this
time. Yes.
But still, why does it need to be יהודה Yehudah that applies
elsewhere in...
We're going to get to why יהודה. Yehudah. Okay.
Are they really טובל tovel these things? They're talking about like a
גת gat and a בד. bad.
Oh, the stone things don't become טמא. tamei. Things that are attached
to the ground don't become טמא, tamei, but it's the vessels that
you, it's the vessels that you put it in. Ah, okay. All
right. Now, עברו הגתות והבדים. avru hagittot v'habadim.
Now, this period has passed. והביא לו חבית של יין של תרומה.
v'heivi lo chavit shel yayin shel terumah. And they bring to a
כהן, Kohen, this עם הארץ am ha'aretz brings to a כהן Kohen
a whole big barrel of wine. But oh, you should have brought
it to me a week ago. That was still the time of
the pressing. Now I have to assume it's a week later, it's
after the season. I have to assume it's טמא. tamei. I can't
accept your תרומה. terumah, What am I going to do? So, והביא
לו חבית, לא יקבלנה ממנו. v'heivi lo chavit, lo yekabelenah mimenu. I
can't accept it from you. Now I have to assume it's טמא.
tamei. It doesn't, here's the irony. It was produced three weeks ago.
It doesn't matter. It doesn't matter. That because then it gets so
confusing, what you got to like label everything exactly when it was
produced, whoever is checking the date.
Yeah, exactly. Then you know what they didn't do at those times?
What we do is we'll do the old, was it a UPC
symbol? So we'll have everything tagged. No, excuse me. So what they
did was they said it's based on the time that you are,
basically not the time it was produced, but the time you're getting
it, meaning the time they're making the claim and giving it to
you and saying this is טהור. tahor If they say that during
the right period, they're believed; during the wrong period, they're not believed.
So here it goes, the guy brings it to me. He made
it three weeks ago. Now he's bringing it to me. I can't
take it. I can't believe him now. So what do you do?
So, מניחה לגת הבאה. manichah lagat haba'ah. You tell him, you know
what? Do me a favor, please. Hold on to this and give
it back to me next time at, like, you know, ten months
from now when it's the next pressing period. The exact same stuff?
The exact same stuff. But then I'll be able to believe you.
I can't believe you now. I can't take it now. I can't
accept... If... what can I tell you? You gotta have some rules.
ואם אמר לו. v'im amar lo. But let's say what the עם
הארץ am ha'aretz tells you is, he says, you know what? This
barrel of wine, before I brought this to you for תרומה, terumah
from the same barrel I took out like a little bottle, a
little cup worth of wine that I was, that I sanctified for,
for קודש, for נסכים. nesachim. So it says, oh, thank you. That's
great. Now since I believed you about the קודש that you separated
out, and that I can believe you the whole year by קודש,
I can believe you now that the whole barrel was טהור. tahor,
Okay. So נאמן. ne'eman. He's believed. כדי יין. kadei yayin. Maybe you
also wonder if there's like a little wink and a nod, like,
I can't accept it now unless of course you were to take
out some wine and sanctify it for קודש, then I would be
able to accept it. Oh, okay. Well no, you can't pay for
תרומה. terumah, Okay. So נאמן. ne'eman. כדי יין וכדי שמן המדומעות kadei
yayin v'chadei shemen hameduma'ot נאמנים. ne'emanim. If you have barrels of wine
and oil that are mixed, you're believed. Now normally what mixed means
is it means חולין and תרומה terumah, mixed or that have never
been separated out. So why you would believe, be believed when it
is not yet separated or had been mixed together after separate but
you wouldn't believe if it was תרומה terumah is not at all
clear. So we're going to see about that in the גמרא. Gemara.
נאמנים עליהם בשעת הגתות והבדים. ne'emanim aleihen b'sha'at hagittot v'habadim. Ah, now
here it says you are believed at the time of pressing. So
maybe what it's saying is the same way you're believed on the
תרומה, terumah. you're believed when it is pre-separated תרומה terumah, and it
is מדומעת, meduma'at, okay, or it is תרומה terumah that then got
mixed up with חולין. So it's the same time period that you
would be believed about תרומה, terumah the time of the pressing. וקודם
לגתות שבעים יום. v'kodem lagittot shiv'im yom. What this also adds and
it's not clear if this also refers to the earlier point, it
seems like it does not, that in this special case of being
mixed, you're even believed 70 days prior to the actual pressing. Now,
okay, now it's possible that that is going back to modify even
the general time of being believed, but it's interesting that it waited
till here. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Rabbi, yes.
What compels an, what compels an עם הארץ am ha'aretz to give
תרומה other than religious integrity? Religious integrity! It's not like they
weren't
פרום, frum, you know. It's,
first of all, we have to correct some assumptions. Right. Number one
is that they were ignorant. Okay. Now they might have not as
been as... People who don't know how to read a
תוספות Tosafot aren't necessarily ignorant. People in their audience could be ten
times more intelligent than them. They just have never learned how to
read a תוספות, Tosafot, you know? So number one is that they,
you know, A, they, you know, educated, intelligent, they probably were wealthier
than the rabbis, better in business and all those types of things.
They just either were not as informed about details of טומאה וטהרה
tumah v'taharah or weren't as scrupulous about details of טומאה וטהרה, tumah
v'taharah, maybe a little bit of both. That's basically the difference between
the עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, okay?
So, but they have,
but they were totally, they were totally
פרום. frum. They're פרום frum about הלכות שבת, hilchot Shabbat, they're פרום
frum about הלכות כשרות, hilchot kashrut, they're פרום frum about this, they're
פרום frum about that. Now, the area that they weren't so scrupulous
in was טומאה וטהרה, tumah v'taharah, and the גמרא Gemara also assumes
a certain degree, you know, percentage weren't as careful about separating out
תרומות ומעשרות. trumot u'ma'asrot. Now, why there, again, we tend to sort
of, I think, extend from that and say, oh, so in general
they're not פרום, frum, they don't separate out תרומות ומעשרות. trumot u'ma'asrot.
But first of all, the גמרא Gemara said it was only a
minority of them, number one. Number two, it says everybody was believed
in תרומה, to separate תרומה because that was a tiny amount. The
question was whether they believed to separate out מעשר, ma'aser, which was
twenty percent, there were two מעשרות. ma'asrot. So there, it says a
minority of them, not a majority, were not believed. But one of
course imagines that there was a real serious financial aspect there, right?
To give up twenty percent of your annual income, right? So to
assume that because that there was concerns about them separating מעשר ma'aser
and there was concerns about their scrupulousness by טהרה taharah means that
they were generally not observant or not פרום, frum, I don't think
is a legitimate, I don't think it's legitimate, right. So let's take
a look now at the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay. ביהודה הן ובגליל לא. B'Yehuda hein u'baGalil lo. So
ביהודה הן ובגליל לא. B'Yehuda hein u'baGalil lo. So only in Judea
do we have this greater leniency around תרומה, not in the Galilee.
And maybe also, and maybe not only about the תרומה, maybe also
about believing them, actually more what the גמרא Gemara is going to
focus on is believing them about קודש for the whole year. That's
a special leniency by ביהודה b'Yehuda not in the גליל. Galil. Why?
מאי טעמא, what's the reason? אמר ריש לקיש מפני שרצועה של כותים
מפסקת ביניהם. amar Reish Lakish mipnei sheretzu'a shel kutim mafseket beineihem.
So because in the גליל Galil is, Jerusalem isn't in the גליל,
Galil, it's in יהודה, Yehuda, and the גליל, Galil, there's a strip
of land of Samaritans that separates the גליל Galil from יהודה. Yehuda.
And therefore, that has a status הלכתית halachicly as ארץ העמים, eretz
ha'amim, as not, it's fascinating because it's in the boundaries of ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but because it is culturally not by Jews or
Samaritans which were a whole question about their status, it's considered to
essentially be non-Jewish territory. And therefore the הלכה halacha is when you
go into non-Jewish territory, usually it means outside of Israel, we consider
the ground of ארץ העמים טמא, eretz ha'amim tamei, okay? And therefore
if you go there, you're טמא. tamei. If you were to bring
תרומה or קדשים kodshim there, it would become טמא. tamei. So here's
the thing. Why do we believe people about their קודש, that it's
טהור? tahor. Because to enable them to bring it to the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash. right? But if you made stuff קודש in the
גליל, Galil, there's no way you'd be able to bring it to
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So we have no impetus to believe
that it's טהור because either way you're not going to be able
to bring it to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash You could only
get it there through transporting it through the ארץ העמים eretz ha'amim
and that would make it טמא, tamei, right? And B, I forget
what the B is. Anyway, there's no impetus for us to believe
you in that case that it is טהור, okay?
So. Even if you're taking it on a wagon the whole way
through, the moment it passes?
Exactly. So now the גמרא, Gemara, so therefore there's no reason to
believe you by קודש because, because anyway there's no, the whole reason
we believe you is because it could be brought to the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash? and we have to deal with the implications of
that.
Now how would someone from the גליל Galil bring anything into the
בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash? They'd have to go up to Jerusalem and
buy things there.
Basically. Yeah. That would be exactly what they would have to do.
Wouldn't that also apply to the מעשר שני ma'aser sheni or something
like that, right?
Yeah, but you're post, so you bring the money and you buy
your stuff.
You can never actually bring the מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni.
That's what the גמרא Gemara is saying. That is correct. So let's
take a look at what the גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא
Gemara says, I mean the גמרא Gemara will deal with shouldn't there
be some way to transport it safely? So let's take a look.
All right. That's a good question. Let's take a look. So the
גמרא Gemara says,
וליתיב בשידה תיבה ומגדל? v'leiseiv b'shida teiva u'migdal? Why don't you bring
it in like in a box and a chest, but it means
like a, you know, like a, like a cabinet? Basically you put
it in something and you carry it, you know, in a wagon,
or you carry it in a box and it never touches the
ground. It's always suspended above the ground. So the גמרא Gemara says
no. הא מני רבי היא, ha meni Rabbi hi, it's Rabbi. דאמר
אהל זרוק לאו שמיה אהל. d'amar ohel zaruk lav shemei ohel. A
thrown אהל, ohel, an אהל ohel that is not rooted in the,
that's not on the ground, is not an אהל. ohel. Right? Because
if you've got טומאה tumah here
and there's a, it's in a house, right?
And here I am on the house, right? A טומאת מת, tumat
meit, because טומאת ארץ העמים tumat eretz ha'amim was like טומאת מת,
tumat meit, it was considered that there were dead bodies buried there.
So it hits the roof, it spreads throughout the
house,
but... Is that an אהל, ohel, does it stop the טומאה tumah
and cause it to spread, or is it not an אהל ohel
because it's not rooted on the ground and the טומאה tumah goes
through? Guess what we have as modern-day flying carpets? Airplanes! Fly over
cemeteries, אהל זרוק, ohel zaruk, does it stop the טומאה tumah and
cause it to spread or not, or does it go through? So
that's the case of here I am, I'm transferring my קודש, my
wine and oil in ארץ העמים eretz ha'amim and here I am,
I'm walking with it, okay, and does it stop the טומאה tumah
because it hits the bottom of the box, or is this suspended
in air, right? So it doesn't stop the טומאה tumah and it's
going to be מטמא metamei, it. So רבי Rebbe says a thrown
אהל ohel is not an אהל ohel and the טומאה tumah will
hit me through the flying carpet and it'll hit this even if
I'm carrying it in a box. Okay, let's just read that.
Wait, what if some of us mothers go over the bridge, right?
Exactly.
That was a bridge. A bridge isn't thrown. A bridge is ultimately
rooted in the ground. Okay, right. I mean, yeah, it could have
air underneath it, you know, you could have like a tent or
a canopy, but it's got to be its base has to be
connected to the ground.
So the issue isn't whether it's open or closed?
No,
no, the חיבור. hibbur. Exactly, exactly. You know, if
you had, if you had an umbrella, right, that was, that was
linked on the ground or whatever, at the beach, that would be,
that would be an אהל ohel because it's connected to the ground
structurally. But if it wasn't connected to the ground?
Oh, that's why you can open a baby carriage on שבת!
Shabbos! Ah, I'm not going there. Okay. דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in
a ברייתא, braisa, הנכנס לארץ העמים בשידה תיבה ומגדל,
ha-nichnas
le-eretz
ha-amim be-shiddah teivah u-migdal, you go,
actually you yourself get carried like, you know, in a box through
the ארץ העמים eretz ha-amim suspended off the ground. רבי Rebbe מטמא,
רבי Rebbe says you're טמא. tamei. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose
bar Rabbi Yehudah מטהר, metaher, you're טהור. But according to רבי, Rebbe,
it won't be able to transfer it. The גמרא Gemara says וליתו
בכלי חרס המוקף צמיד פתיל, ve-leisu be-khli heresh ha-mukaf tzamit patil, why
not bring it in a pottery vessel that is sealed with a
like airtight seal? Okay, with a so and when, not airtight literally,
but whatever, a tight seal. Remember a pottery vessel only becomes טמא
tamei through their, through their airspace, right? Through something gets into the,
the טומאה has to go into the cavity. And if there is
a tight seal on the opening of a pottery vessel, טומאה can't
get in from the outside and it can't get in from the
inside. The tight seal is seen as protecting the inside. So why
not just bring it in a tightly sealed pottery vessel? So אמר
רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar, שונים, shonin, because we teach אין קודש
ניצול בצמיד פתיל. ein kodesh nitzol be-tzamit patil.
Sanctified objects cannot be protected by this seal. This is another, I
don't know, it's another stringency. So the גמרא Gemara says what can
I tell you? ותנן, Ve-hatnan, but don't one minute, we teach in
a משנה אין חטאת ניצלת בצמיד פתיל, ein hattas nitzeles be-tzamit patil,
that the water of the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah cannot be protected
by the צמיד פתיל. tzamit patil. So that's the highest level of
thing cannot be protected. Presumably קודש can be protected. מאי לאו, Mai
lav, does it not imply הקודש ניצול, ha kodesh nitzol, that קודש
can be saved by a צמיד פתיל? tzamit patil? It's only the
פרה אדומה Parah Adumah that cannot be saved. The גמרא Gemara says
לא, no, it means המים שאינם מקודשים ניצולין בצמיד פתיל. ha-mayim she-einan
mekudashin nitzolin be-tzamit patil. If you have the water that you're that
you have not yet mixed the ashes in, the water you're going
to use for the חטאת, but the ashes haven't yet been mixed
in, then it's not sanctified fully, then it's not at this high
level and then it will be protected. But once the ashes are
moved in, it won't be protected. But that's not only something about
פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, it also applies to קודש in general. קודש
is at such a high level it cannot be protected with this
צמיד פתיל. tzamit patil. And that's why there's no way to bring
the קודש in through ארץ העמים. eretz ha-amim. You can't bring it
in a box, you can't bring it in a pottery vessel, it
won't be protected.
צמיד פתיל Tzamit patil means that it's sealed?
Yes, tightly sealed, yep. ואמר עולא, Ve-amar Ulla, and doesn't עולא Ulla
say חברייא מדקין בגלילא? haveraya medakkin be-Galila? One minute, he says that
the חברים haverim purify their stuff in the Galilee. So, now of
course so how, why would they be purifying it if there's no
way to bring it to the בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash It's very
funny because עולא Ulla was, what, 200 years after חורבן הבית? Hurban
ha-Bayit? So for you know why are they sanctifying stuff at all?
Forget whether it's in the Galilee or Judea, but okay, I don't
know the answer. Anyway the גמרא Gemara says מניחין, manichin, anyway you're
doing, you know like I said there's no בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
anyway, so fine. מניחין להן שיבוא אליהו ויטהרנה. manichin le-hen she-yavo Eliyahu
ve-yitaharena. Fine, they
sanctify their stuff and they're leaving it in some safe and when
אליהו הנביא Eliyahu HaNavi comes he'll show us how to get it
from the Galilee to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash without making it
טמא. tamei. Okay, but basically the leniency here, so there's two חידושים,
chiddushim, one is that קודש is more lenient than תרומה. We've always
said it's more strict, but when it comes to believing the עם
הארץ am ha-aretz it's more lenient. But this leniency is only in
Judea where they have access to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and
they is a need in order to accept and you know they
can bring it to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, and there's a
need in order to accept it. When it comes to the issue
of תרומה, presumably by תרומה which doesn't need a בית המקדש, there
we believe no matter where you are, but we believe you during
the period of the pressing of the oil and of the wine,
of the olives and of the grapes. So the קודש thing is
only in יהודה Yehudah and that's the whole year, the תרומה thing
is during the pressing of the olives and the grapes, and that
is and that is presumably regardless of where you are. Okay, I
guess we'll have to end here. So I keep on hoping we'll
get